Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes.
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program.
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program,
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen.
Lesson 1 - Score Setup
The first thing you’ll see when you open
MuseScore 2.0 is the new Start Center.
Here you can create a new score,
open an existing score,
or connect with the online community at musescore.com.
Let’s create a new score
Enter the title and credits first
Click the next button and here we can either
use one of the templates that are included
or we can just simply choose our own instruments
To select instruments, first click on the instrument family and then select the instrument you want
and click the Add button
If you want to move an instrument up or down,
just simply click on it
and press the up and down button
You can also add a staff or a linked staff
which can be very useful for adding things like tab staffs
Now select a key signature
You can also set the tempo here
Finally enter the time signature
pickup measure
and the number of measures you want for your piece
Now remember, we can always change anything we have just done at any time
Now Click Finish
You can return to the Start Center
or the instrument window
to make changes, add instruments,
or remove instruments
Our score is pretty basic right now.
You’ll notice the measure spacing is rather
unusual
Don’t worry about that as it will change automatically as we enter notes and
other things
But you might want to add brackets
to adjust the barlines
To add bracket, we go to the palette
and select the bracket and drag it to the first staff
Then double-click it and drag down
until it covers all of the staves
You can add more than one bracket
so I'll add one here to our guitar and do the same thing
Use the same method to extend barlines
Double click one and drag down
You'll see that it now adjusts all of the barlines
If you want to select separate groups,
you can do that too
So we now have our basic score
and we're ready to enter in our notes.